Finding Aid for Woodrow W. Hunter Papers 1947-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Organizations
  - First Presbyterian Church, Ann Arbor 1967-1979
    - Committee on housing the aging 1975-1977
      - General (Box 7)
      - Minutes (Box 7)
    - Housing needs of older people, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Housing surveys-Others (Box 7)
    - Housing the aging (Box 7)
    - Housing the aging questionnaire (Box 7)
    - Questionnaire for the homebound (Box 7)
    - Retirement center 1975-1979 (Box 7)
    - Retirement facility committee 1968-1970 (Box 7)
    - Survey of the aging 1968 (Box 7)
    - Survey of churches 1962 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Commission on Aging Education Task Force 1963-1964, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Michigan Nursing Home Administrators Advisory Council 1973 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Society of Gerontology
    - Board of Directors meeting minutes 1966-1967 (Box 8)
    - Community Organization Committee 1962-1963, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Correspondence 1953-1957 (Box 8)
    - Founding (Box 8)
    - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Oliver Wendell Holmes Association Advisory Council 1968 (Box 8)
  - U.M./W.S.U. Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations 1956-1960 (Box 8)
  - Washtenaw County Citizens Advisory Committee for Social Services 1970-1971 (Box 8)
  - Washtenaw County Council on Aging 1969 (Box 8)
- Institute of Gerontology
  The Institute of Gerontology series contains files relating to the activities and administration of the Institute. The greater part of the material covers the 1970s, including Hunter's tenure as acting co-director in 1971-1974, and the Residential Institute program.
  - Annual Conferences 1971-1974
    - 24th Annual Conference 1971
      - Budget (Box 8)
      - Discussion Leaders (Box 8)
    - 25th Annual Conference 1972
      - Budget (Box 8)
      - Correspondence (Box 8)
      - Memoranda (Box 8)
      - Pioneers (Box 8)
      - Program, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Roster (Box 8)
    - 26th Annual Conference 1973
      - Budget (Box 8)
      - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - 27th Annual Conference 1974
      - Budget (Box 8)
  - Archives (Box 8)
  - Budgets 1967-1973 (Box 8)
  - Co-director search 1974 (Box 8)
  - Course material
    - Demography-Brahce 1974 (Box 8)
    - Goals of applied social gerontology-Havighurst circa 1974 (Box 8)
    - Older adults as consumers-Plummer 1976 (Box 8)
    - Philosophy of aging-Philibert 1973 Summer Institute (Box 8)
    - Pre-retirement education workshop--various 1973 (Box 8)
    - Programs and services for the aged-Vasey 1973 (Box 8)
    - Seminar in social gerontology-unknown undated (Box 8)
    - Social gerontology-Tibbitts 1973 (Box 8)
    - Training program on needs of elderly-Wright State undated (Box 8)
  - Curriculum Committee 1976 (Box 8)
  - Division of Statewide Programs and Services 1973-1977, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Evaluation and planning project-phase 1 1976 (Box 8)
  - General, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Gifts (Box 8)
  - Grants (Box 8)
  - Hunter's consultant work for IOG 1979 (Box 8)
  - Memos 1971-1974, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Papers undated (Box 8)
    (a large bound set of papers, including three by Hunter)
  - Placement service in aging 1970 (Box 8)
  - Planning (Box 8)
  - Postgraduate survey of training 1969-1971 (Box 8)
  - Prokop's biographical sketch of Tibbitts (Box 8)
  - Residential Institute
    - 1967-1969 (Box 9)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 9)
    - 1972 (Box 9)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 9)
  - Staff meetings 1969-1974 (Box 9)
  - Task forces 1972 (Box 9)
  - Training program for specialists in aging 1966-1967 (Box 9)
  - Wayne State University
    - Correspondence (Box 9)
    - Proposals (Box 9)
- Manuscripts (not Hunter)
  The series Manuscripts (Not Hunter) contains some forty manuscripts of papers on gerontology, collected but not written by Hunter. They are arranged alphabetically by author's name.
  - Alexander and Alexander. The revolt of the old 1977 (Box 9)
  - Ann Arbor Lifelong Learning. Second quarterly report 1969 (Box 9)
  - Charles, Don. Effect of participation in a pre-retirement program 1971 (Box 9)
  - Cook, John. Exxon proposal 1979 (Box 9)
    includes correspondence
  - Donahue, Wilma. Handbook of applied social gerontology (grant proposal) 1961 (Box 9)
  - Drake University. A guide to program development for pre-retirement planning 1969 (Box 9)
  - Eastern Illinois University. Pre-retirement education leadership development (proposal) 1979 (Box 9)
  - Everett Junior College (Washington). Yesterday, today, and tomorrow 1962 (Box 9)
  - Fillenbaum, Gerda. A comparison of the effects of two retirement systems 1973 (Box 9)
  - Heffernan, Sister Mary. An analytical model on educational program planning for the aged 1971 (Box 9)
  - Johnson, Harold and Cohen, Wilbur. Ford Foundation proposal 1975 (Box 9)
  - Katon, Joseph. Making a plan and putting it into effect 1962 (Box 9)
  - Katona, George and Morgan, James. Retirement in prospect and retrospect circa 1967 (Box 9)
  - McConnell, John. Research emphases in pre-retirement planning programs 1959 (Box 9)
  - McQueen, Constance. An historical perspective of the Institute for Study of Older Adults 1972 (Box 9)
  - Michigan Office of Service to the Aging. Educational services for older people (120 pp.), ca 1975 (Box 9)
  - Miller, Sydney. Dissertation proposal 1975 (Box 9)
  - Nagler, Phyllis. Pre-retirement education guide circa 1977, 230 pages (Box 9)
  - Nassau County (NY) Office for the Aging. A pre-retirement clinic in an adult education setting 1968 (Box 9)
  - National Council on Aging. Exploration of simulation as a retirement education technique 1967 (Box 9)
  - Newfield, Ken. Orientation to later life 1971 (Box 9)
  - Orbach, Harold. Social and institutional aspects of industrial workers' retirement programs undated (Box 9)
  - Pattinson, Diane. Untitled manuscript on mandatory retirement undated (Box 9)
  - Peterson, David. Financial adequacy in retirement perceptions of older Americans circa 1970 (Box 9)
  - Phillips, Bernard. Research strategy for determining factors involved in successful preparation for retirement 1959 (Box 9)
  - Pollack, Otto. Retirement: the emerging social pattern circa 1959 (Box 9)
  - Reich, Murray. A pre-retirement action program 1976 (Box 9)
  - Reich, Murray. Group pre-retirement counseling programs circa 1977 (Box 9)
  - Sahara, Penny. Media sources for gerontology circa 1972 (Box 9)
  - Schultz, Edwin. A study of programs of preparation for retirement in industry 1963 (Box 9)
  - Tibbitts, Clark. Middle-aged and older people in American society 1965 (Box 9)
  - UAW. Discussion leaders outline for steward training circa 1950 (Box 9)
  - U.S. Civil Service Commission. A catalog of training methods 1957 (Box 9)
  - University of Minnesota. A multi-university proposal for educating workers for retirement circa 1960 (Box 9)
  - University of Southern California. Pre-retirement planning programs 1976 (Box 9)
  - Weisberg, Betsy. Satisfaction in retirement 1972 (Box 9)
  - Wolf, Betty and Umhau. A look at pre-retirement planning in the laboratory method (Box 9)
  - Anonymous. Pre-retirement education survey undated (Box 9)
  - Anonymous. Retirement career center undated (Box 9)
- Other Media
  The Other Media series in box 10 consists of photographs, films and sound recordings of programs and conferences on pre-retirement training and gerontology in general. They include audio-cassettes, reel-to-reel tapes, and 16 mm films.
  - Photographs (Box 10)
  - Audio-tapes
    - "Looking Forward to Retirement", 10 audiocassettes
      - Tape 1: Work Versus Retirement: Expectations and Personal Viewpoints (parts 1 and 2) (Box 10)
      - Tape 2: Food and Nutrition for the Elderly (parts I and 2) (Box 10)
      - Tape 3: Good Health During Retirement (parts 1 and 2) (Box 10)
      - Tape 4: Social Security and Medicare (parts I and 2) (Box 10)
      - Tape 5: University Pension, Health and Life Insurance Benefits (parts 1 and 2) (Box 10)
      - Tape 6: Legal Affairs of the Older Person (parts 1 and 2) (Box 10)
      - Tape 7: Legal Affairs of the Older Person (part 3) and Financial Planning (part 1) (Box 10)
      - Tape 8: Financial Planning (part 2) (Box 10)
      - Tape 9: Friends, Family, and Living Arrangements (parts 1 and 2) (Box 10)
      - Tape 10: Free Time and summary (parts I and 2) (Box 10)
      - Various conferences, mainly early 1950s, reel-to-reel tapes, 7 in. (Box 10)
  - Films
    - "Preparation for Retirement" UM Television (16 mm films; sound, black and white)
      - 1. (Silent) Retired man sitting in the living room and getting in his wife's way as she prepares for some sort of party (Box 10)
      - 2. Retired And Home All Day. Retired husband is sitting around the house while his wife makes ready to have her friends come in., 2 copies (Box 10)
      - 3. Older Worker And Pressures On The Job. Industrial shop scene: the pressure which an older worker feels trying to keep up on his job., 6 copies (Box 10)
      - 4. Retired And Living With One's Children. Situations which arise when an older man goes to live with his children., 2 copies (Box 10)
      - 5. Health During The Retirement Years. Situation in which an older man experiences dizziness and pain in his legs. Provokes discussion of self-diagnosis, fear of going to doctor, use of patent medicine, etc. (2 copies) (Box 10)
      - 6. Financial Planning For The Later Years. A situation in which an older man and wife realize the need for financial planning., 3 copies (Box 10)
      - 7. The Last Day On The Job. What happens the last day on the job., 3 copies (Box 10)
      - 8. The 64th Birthday. The 64th birthday and how a man and his wife react. We use this as an introductory film in our pre-retirement planning courses because it provokes discussion of the need to plan, the way people feel about retirement, etc., 2 copies (Box 10)